Mistress Frieren…
芙莉莲大人…
That took a while.
你们好慢啊
I see you defeated Aura.
看来您打败阿乌拉了
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
Unbelievable… Who'd have thought this was possible?
真是难以置信 居然真的打赢了？
Let's go.
走吧
Wait, there's no need to run.
等一下 你已经没必要逃跑了
Graf Granat said he'd pardon you.
伯爵说了不会再追究之前的事情
It must've been a fierce battle
想必发生了一场激烈的战斗吧
but they are all mostly intact.
但他们却全都毫发无伤
I appreciate it.
谢谢你
Thank you for showing honor to the heroes of the northern lands.
谢谢你对北方诸国的英杰们 所展现出的尊重
Before, I used to make a bigger mess.
以前我出手的场面可是很壮观呢
But Himmel got mad at me.
但是辛美尔对我发了好大的脾气
Of course he would. I don't blame him for getting mad.
那是当然的 会发脾气也是在情理之中
I'd get mad too.
换作是我也会生气的
Master Himmel did a good job training you.
辛美尔大人 把芙莉莲大人教得很好呢
Don't call it training.
不准说是“教”
But I guess you're right…
不过 说得也是啦
That's a normal response.
那才是正常反应
What do you mean?
什么意思？
Don't mind me.
不用理我
Fern, Stark,
菲伦 休塔尔克
good job defeating Lügner and Linie.
你们把琉古纳他们打败了呢
I'm proud of you.
真是了不起
It would've been better if you weren't so beat up.
要是没有这么狼狈就更好了
This is normal for a warrior.
身为战士 这样很正常
-What is "normal"? -You're covered in wounds.
-“正常”是什么意思？ -你浑身是伤耶
Give them a proper burial.
好好厚葬他们
-I will escort them to town. -Yes, sir.
-我要护送他们返城 -遵命
Your Excellency…
阁下…
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Frieren,
芙莉莲
I've never wanted to thank someone as much as I do today.
我从来没有像今天这样感谢一个人
it is true
我确实说过
that I said I would do whatever I can to reward you.
会给予你我力所能及的奖赏
And you requested for
而你要求的是
Great Mage Flamme's Grimoire about defense barriers,
古拉纳特家族代代相传
which has been passed down
由大魔法使伏拉梅所著
in the Granat family for generations.
有关防护结界的魔导书
Are you sure this is what you want?
这种魔导书真的可以吗？
-This grimoire is… -Fake.
-这本魔导书是… -赝品
That's right. It is nothing close to the defense barrier spell
没错 我们家族代代口传的
used on this town, which has been passed down orally.
防护结界魔法 与这本书记载的内容相去甚远
I am well aware of that, Your Excellency.
这点我很清楚 阁下
This is just a hobby of mine.
这纯粹是我个人兴趣罢了
I see.
这样啊
More importantly, there's no need to speak so formally.
你不用这样毕恭毕敬地说话
To you, I'm probably nothing but a baby.
对你而言 我就跟小婴儿没有两样吧
On our departure to defeat the Demon King,
我们当年启程去讨伐魔王时
I learned my lesson.
已经受过教训了
Oh, I remember Master Heiter talking about that.
我记得海塔大人提起过这件事
In the royal capital, disrespecting nobility is a capital offense.
在王都对贵族无礼的话是死罪
Himmel and Eisen
辛美尔跟艾泽
spoke informally to the king and were almost executed.
因为对国王出言不逊 差点就被处死了
How nostalgic. I remember Himmel's face as he wailed.
真令人怀念呢 辛美尔当时哀嚎的脸庞
Capital offense? That must be an exaggeration.
死罪什么的也太夸张了吧
One more thing, you brat.
还有一件事 臭小鬼
Using informal speech with me is a serious crime in this town.
跟我说话这样没大没小 在这座城里可是重罪
Sorry, old man. I'm going to break this fancy chair.
抱歉了 大叔 我要毁了这把贵重的椅子
Who knew the central lands were so savage, Your Excellency?
没想到中央诸国的人 这么野蛮呢 阁下
Are you serious?!
不是吧！
-We've cut down the tree out back. -Good work.
-后院的树已经砍完了 -辛苦了
Anyway,
那个啊
I just said that to give him an excuse to run away.
我当时那么说 只是为了让他快点逃而已
This town doesn't have any law that will imprison you for informal speech.
这座城并没有说话不礼貌 就会下牢的法律啊
Don't worry. You can relax.
不用担心 放轻松点
-Well, if that's the case. -Good for you, Master Stark.
-原来如此 -那真是太好了 休塔尔克大人
He's passed out.
他吓到失神了
We've told the townspeople the news of Aura's defeat.
阿乌拉讨伐成功的消息已经传遍全城
They all can't wait to show the heroes their appreciation.
居民已经等不及要向英雄表达谢意了
Please spend some time here.
请务必要多留一阵子
He's floating!
他在飞耶！
Oh, it was nothing.
那种事没什么啦
All the shopping is done.
东西都买好了
Then let's go.
那我们出发吧
You're departing already, Frieren?
已经要出发了吗 芙莉莲？
Graf Granat.
古拉纳特伯爵
I'll see you to the gate.
我送各位到城门口吧
Frieren,
芙莉莲
I hear you are heading to Ende,
我听说你们要前往
the northernmost point of the continent where the Demon King's castle is.
魔王城堡的所在地 大陆极北之境的厄德
However,
不过
the current state of affairs in the Northern Plateau is quite bad.
目前北部高原的情势相当不妙
So they're limiting travel.
所以他们实施了限制通行
Even adventurers are required
就连冒险者都必须
to be accompanied by a first-class mage.
有一级魔法使同行才能放行
Well then, it shouldn't be a problem since we have Mistress Frieren.
我们有芙莉莲大人在 一定没问题
What is a "first-class mage"?
那个“一级魔法使”是什么？
Mistress Frieren, you don't know?
芙莉莲大人不知道吗？
It's a certification for mages set by
是大陆魔法协会
the Continental Magic Association.
所颁发的魔法使资格证书
-Certification? -I got mine when I left home.
-证书？ -我在出发前
In the Holy City.
也去圣都考试了
See?
你看
It's a certification for a third-class mage.
这是三级魔法使证书
Now that I think about it, that sounds familiar.
这样说起来 我好像听你说过这么一回事呢
Certifications look like this now, huh?
现在的证书长这样啊？
Mistress Frieren, don't tell me you are an uncertified underground mage?
芙莉莲大人难道是 没被认证的地下魔法使？
Don't say it like I'm an underground doctor.
不要说得好像 我是什么无照行医的医生
I mean, organizations that manage mages are constantly changing.
毕竟管理魔法使的组织经常在变
I can't afford to get certified each time.
我哪有办法每次都去考呢
And I bet this Holy Emblem isn't valid anymore, right?
那么这个圣杖证明也不能用了吧？
What is that relic?
那个古董是什么东西？
Even I know about the Continental Magic Association.
就连我也知道大陆魔法协会呢
They've been around for at least half a century.
他们至少存在超过半世纪了
That's very recent.
那根本就是最近的事嘛
It's so troublesome
真麻烦
when they change management systems so frequently.
管理基准老是一直改来改去
Either way, we can't get anywhere like this.
总之 这样我们哪里都去不了
I'm not that knowledgeable in this area,
我对这一带不是那么了解
but the northern lands should have
但是北方诸国应该有
a place to take the first-class mage exam, right?
可以参加一级魔法使考试的地方吧？
The largest city of magic in the northern lands,
北方诸国最大的魔法之都
Äußerst, is the location.
奥伊萨斯特就是了
NORTHERN LANDS - CENTRAL LANDS
（北方诸国 - 中央诸国）
It's way past the Schwer Mountains.
穿过休维亚山脉后
You just have to go along the main road, but it'll be a long trip.
只要沿着主要干道走就可以了 但是要走上很久才会到
Frieren,
芙莉莲
the Granat family is forever indebted to you.
古拉纳特家族会永远铭记这份恩情
Have a safe trip.
祝你们一路平安
It's snowing.
下雪了
It's almost winter.
差不多快入冬了
Winter in this region is harsh, so be careful.
这里的冬天非常寒冷 要注意喔
-If you take it lightly, you'll die. -It's that dangerous?
-小看寒冷的话 可是会死人的 -有这么危险吗？
You don't know?
你不知道啊？
In the war against the Demon King's army, most of the people died because of
和魔王军的战争中 大部分的人
the winter in the northern lands.
都是死于北方诸国的冬季
You see? We're lost.
看吧？我们迷路了
What should we do?
怎么办啊？
We're lost.
迷路了呢
28 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO DECKE REGION IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（勇者辛美尔逝世的28年后 北方诸国 蒂克地区）
We're lost and we haven't even entered the Schwer Mountains.
还没进到休维亚山脉就迷路了
This isn't even funny.
这一点都不好笑
Master Stark! Wake up! You'll die if you fall asleep.
休塔尔克大人 醒醒！ 睡着的话会死掉的
Was the jumbo berry special always this small…?
超大莓果特制圣代以前就这么小吗…
How would I know?
那种事谁知道啊？
What should we do?
怎么办？
The wind is so strong, we can't suspend him in the air with magic.
风太强了 恐怕也不能用魔法搬运他
He'll get blown away somewhere.
这样他会被吹走的
I guess we have to carry him.
看来只能扛着他走了
He's heavy.
他好重
Why is he so heavy?
这个人怎么这么重？
It smells good…
闻起来好香喔…
-Can I leave him here? -Bear with him.
-我可以把他丢下吗？ -你就忍忍吧
There's a shelter at the foot of the mountain.
山脚下有个避难的小屋
That information is from 80 years ago, right?
那是八十年前的情报吧？
Are we going to be okay?
真的没问题吗？
Thank goodness.
谢天谢地
It seems they take care of it regularly.
看来有人定期管理呢
There seems to be someone in there.
里面好像已经有人在了
Did someone beat us to it?
有人先进去了吗？
Let's just go inside.
总之就先进去吧
We'll freeze to death at this rate.
这样下去我们会冻僵的
This is great! I'm getting warm!
太棒了…开始暖和起来了！
Excuse me.
打扰了
Mistress Frieren, this place is no good.
芙莉莲大人 这个地方不行
Let's go somewhere else.
我们去别的地方吧
-What? Why? -Because there is a pervert in there.
-怎么了？为什么？ -因为里面有个变态啊
Who are you calling a pervert?
你这是在叫谁变态啊？
Let's go, Mistress Frieren.
我们走吧 芙莉莲大人
Wait. Are you an elf?
等一下 你是精灵？
It's been about 300 years since I last saw another elf.
我大概三百年没见过同族了
I thought elves had already gone extinct.
我还以为精灵族已经灭绝了
Me too.
我也是
Thank you for the fire, young lady.
小姐的火帮了大忙呢
You're welcome.
不客气
I'm lucky to have come across mages.
能够遇上魔法使真是太幸运了
It must be thanks to the Goddess.
一切都多亏了女神大人啊
I crossed the Schwer Mountains
我翻过了休维亚山脉
but my fire died out with this blizzard.
但是火种却因为这场暴风雪而熄灭了
So I was preserving my life by doing squats in this freezing cabin.
所以刚才只好在 这间寒冷的小屋里做深蹲来保命
I see.
原来如此
I still don't get it.
我还是完全听不懂
I'm Kraft, a monk.
我是武僧克拉伏特
I'm Frieren, a mage.
我是魔法使芙莉莲
I'm Fern, also a mage.
我叫菲伦 我也是魔法使
This is Master Stark, a warrior.
这位是战士休塔尔克大人
So you're on a journey to Aureole, or heaven, huh?
所以你们要前往灵魂长眠之地 也就是天国 对吗？
It's good to have strong faith.
如此虔诚是件好事呢
I don't completely believe it though.
其实我并没有那么虔诚
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉莲大人
Master Stark's temperature is…
休塔尔克大人的体温…
It's warm and relaxing.
好温暖、好舒服喔
And look at that huge jumbo berry special.
还有那杯超大莓果特制圣代
What…
我…
happened to me?
发生什么事了？
I remember we were in a blizzard…
记得好像有暴风雪…
Who is this old man?!
这大叔是谁啊？
How noisy.
吵死了
I was kind enough to warm you up with my body heat.
我好心用体温帮你暖和身体
-How rude of you. -Body heat?
-你这是什么态度啊？ -体温？
You've got a nice body, old man.
大叔体态很棒呢
-Master Stark. -I don't mean it like that.
-休塔尔克大人… -我不是那个意思
His body is so well built.
他的身体锻炼得很棒
I bet you're tremendously strong.
你一定超级强吧
What's your name, old man?
大叔叫什么名字啊？
I'm Kraft, a monk.
克拉伏特 我是名武僧
I've never heard of you.
没听过呢
But I'm sure you're a famous monk.
但想必你一定赫赫有名吧
Stark, you stay here and rest.
休塔尔克 你留下来休息吧
You two, can you help me carry the food?
你们两位可以帮我搬食物吗？
My wagon and cargo are nearby.
我的货车跟货物就在附近
I'm really glad I met you all.
能遇到你们真是太好了
We should be able to do something with this frozen food.
这样应该就有办法 处理这些结冻的食物了
Feel free to use it all.
不用客气 尽管拿去用
This should be more than enough.
这样食物应该就很足够了
Crossing over the Schwer Mountains now would be suicidal.
想在这种情况下 翻过休维亚山脉形同自杀
I guess we'll kill time here.
就暂时在这里停留一阵子吧
By the way, Frieren,
话说回来 芙莉莲
do you know about me?
你听过我的事情吗？
-Not at all. -I thought so.
-完全没有 -我想也是
I don't know a thing about you either.
我对你也一无所知
She was a mage in the party of heroes.
她以前是勇者一行中的魔法使
And before that?
在那之前呢？
What are you trying to say?
你想说什么？
I'm just saying, we're elves.
我只是想说我们都是精灵
It's almost been half a year.
眼看就快过半年了
Thanks to you all,
多亏有你们
I survived the long winter in the northern lands.
我才能在北方诸国 平安度过漫漫寒冬
Here.
给
Can you give it to Fern?
你可以转交给菲伦吗？
She's a good girl with strong faith.
她是个十分虔诚的好孩子
Probably because a priest raised her.
应该是因为被僧侣带大的关系吧
She hasn't lost her appreciation for the Goddess.
她一直都很感激女神大人
Kraft, why do you believe in the Goddess?
克拉伏特 你为什么会相信女神大人的存在？
Frieren, you don't believe in it, huh?
芙莉莲 你不相信 对吧？
Aside from the mythical times, the Goddess of Creation
除却神话时代 创世的女神大人
has never actually shown herself
在这世上漫长的历史中
even once in the long history of this world.
连一次都没有出现过
You must be young.
你一定还很年轻
I used to think that way too.
以前我也是那么想的
But now, I believe in the Goddess from the bottom of my heart.
但我现在打从心里 相信女神大人的存在
More like, I really need her to be real.
不对 应该说我需要相信她是存在的
Everyone who knew about all of
过去我有过什么成就
the deeds I achieved and justice I upheld have died.
或是公平正义 知道的人都已经不在这世上了
That's why
正因如此
I want the Goddess to commend me when I die and go to heaven.
我死后去了天国 女神大人就会好好夸赞我
"Well done, Kraft.
“做得好 克拉伏特
You lived a wonderful life,"
你这辈子过得很精采”
she'll say.
这样
You understand, don't you?
你明白的吧 芙莉莲？
Having nobody to remember
没有人记得
the testaments to your existence
你存在过的证据
is just too cruel.
实在太过残酷了
We have
我们
lived a long time up until now.
至今活了那么长一段时间
Kraft, that is just our wishful thinking.
克拉伏特 那只是我们一厢情愿的想法
Yeah.
说得也是呢
You think that way about heaven too?
你也是这么看待天国吗？
Well, whatever.
没关系 无所谓
Tell me about yourself. And I'll tell you about myself.
跟我说说你的事吧 然后我也会告诉你关于我的事
If you don't believe in the Goddess, then I will commend you
如果你不相信女神大人 那我就代替她来
in her place.
好好夸奖你
-Is it surprising? -Yeah.
-很意外吗？ -是啊
Who would've thought that you would fund the reconstruction of this orphanage.
没想到海塔你 竟然会捐款重建这间孤儿院
You're so honest.
你还真诚实
I was also an orphan, after all.
毕竟我也曾经是孤儿
I'm sure the Goddess
我相信女神大人
will commend me for being virtuous and honorable.
会夸奖我活得 这么有品德而且令人敬重呢
What is this Corrupt Priest going off about with a drink in his hand?
这个酒肉僧侣 一边喝酒一边胡说什么啊？
Frieren…
-芙莉莲… -嗯？
Do you have someone who commends you?
有会夸奖你的人吗？
Why all of a sudden?
怎么突然这么问？
You don't seem to believe in the Goddess.
你似乎不相信女神大人的存在
So if you tell me about yourself, I will commend you instead.
如果你愿意告诉我你的事情 我会替她好好夸奖你
I've just been living without purpose.
我就只是漫无目标地过日子
I've done nothing worthy of commendation.
没做过什么值得被夸奖的事情
Even though you're constantly controlling your mana?
尽管你明明一直在限制魔力吗？
To me, that seems like the result of painstaking effort.
在我看来 那就是呕心沥血的成果
It's as if you've devoted your life to it.
就好像你在这件事上倾注了一生
You noticed?
你发现了？
How many years do you think we've been traveling together?
我们一起旅行都几年了？
It's not an interesting story.
那可不是有趣的故事喔
I don't mind. Plus, I want to know for future reference.
我不介意 而且 这种故事也能留给后世作为借镜
-Why? -There's a possibility.
-为什么？ -因为有可能
That my child will become a mage.
我的孩子会成为魔法使啊
Don't priests stay single their whole lives?
僧侣不是要单身一辈子吗？
Why is everyone who serves the Goddess so weird?
侍奉女神大人的家伙 怎么都这么奇怪？
I'll pass.
我就不用了
I already had someone commend me.
以前已经有人夸过我了
I see.
这样啊
That seems like a nice friendship, Frieren.
看来你有个很好的朋友呢 芙莉莲
You should treasure it.
要好好珍惜才是
No, that person is already…
不 那个人已经…
He's in heaven now.
他现在在天国了
Then I will meet him one day.
那么总有一天会再见面的
Yeah.
是啊
I'm going this way.
我走这边
Frieren, I don't think this is the last time we'll meet.
芙莉莲 我认为 这不会是我们最后一次见面
See you in a few hundred years.
几百年后再会
Take care, old man! It was fun!
大叔保重喔 跟你在一起很开心！
Thank you for the pendant!
谢谢你送我吊坠！
A clean white cape.
没有沾上半点污垢的白色披风
The village protecting the Hero's Blade.
守护勇者之剑的村子
It's a gift to reward
这个礼物是用来
a warrior who has worked hard.
犒劳很拼命努力的战士
Don't tell Dad.
不要告诉爸爸
"A Real Hero."
《真正的勇者》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵